

POSTDOCTORAL RESEARCH ASSOCIATE

Dept. of Speech, Language, and Hearing Sciences, Boston University

■ ekearney@bu.edu | 🕯 elaine-kearney.com | 💆 ek_kearney

Speech scientist focused on the sensorimotor control of speech in individuals with acquired motor speech disorders. I conduct both basic science and clincial research that capitalizes on my expertise in behavioral, computational modeling and neuroimaging methods. The long-term aim of my research program is to expand the evidence-based treatment options available to those with communication disorders.

Education

PhD in Speech-Language Pathology

Canada

University of Toronto

Januray 2013–June 2018

- The Speech Movement Disorder and its Rehabilitation in Parkinson's Disease Using Augmented Visual Feedback
- Committee: Drs. Yana Yunusova (Advisor), Luc de Nil, and Luc Tremblay

BSc in Speech and Language Therapy

Ireland

September 2007-June 2011

- Tongue-Plate Contact During Selected Vowels in Typical and Disordered Articulation
- · Advisor: Dr. Alice Lee

University College Cork

Employment

Postdoctoral Research Associate

Boston, MA

January 2018–Present

- Speech Neuroscience Laboratory
- Advisors: Drs. Frank H. Guenther and Jason A. Tourville

Course Instructor Boston, MA

BOSTON UNIVERSITY

BOSTON UNIVERSITY

September 2019-December 2019

Research Methods in Speech-Language Pathology and Audiology, Clinical MSc.

Course Instructor

University of Toronto

September 2017-December 2017

Toronto, Canada

• Principles of Clinical Practice, Clinical MSc.

Research Assistant Toronto, Canada

University of Toronto

January 2013-December 2017

- Vocal Tract Visualization Laboratory, Toronto Rehabilitation Institute
- Project: Visual Feedback Systems in Speech Rehabilitation
- · Advisor: Dr. Yana Yunusova

Teaching Assistant Toronto, Canada

University of Toronto

September 2013-June 2017

- Augmentative and Alternative Communication, Clinical MSc.
- Linguistics in the Workforce: Clinical Practice and Research, BSc.
- · Applied Audiology, Clinical MSc.
- Advanced Principles of Clinical Practice, Clinical MSc.
- Motor Speech Disorders, Clinical MSc.
- Neurocognitive Communication, Clinical MSc.
- · Motor Speech Disorders, Clinical MSc.

Research Assistant Toronto, Canada

SPEECH AND STUTTERING INSTITUTE

June 2012-December 2012

• Project: Motor Speech Treatment Protocol for Developmental Motor Speech Disorders

Advisor: Dr. Aravind Namasivayam

Research Awards and Honors

Professional Development and Postdoctoral Affairs Travel Award

Boston, MA August 2019

BOSTON UNIVERSITY

• 500 USD

Rehabilitation Sciences Institute Presentation Award

Toronto, Canada

May 2017

May 2017

University of Toronto

• 300 CAD

Rehabilitation Sciences Institute Peer Mentorship Award

Toronto, Canada

University of Toronto

• 100 CAD

Polatajko-Howell Student Conference Presentation Fund

Toronto, Canada June 2017

UNIVERSITY OF TORONTO

• 300 CAD

ASHA's Research Mentoring: Pathways Program

USA

AMERICAN SPEECH-LANGUAGE-HEARING ASSOCIATION

June 2019

Travel, accommodation and food costs for duration of workshop
 Office of Research Trainees Conference Travel Award

Toronto, Canada

University Health Network

March 2016

• 500 CAD

Graduate Scholarship Prize

Toronto, Canada

TORONTO REHABILITATION INSTITUTE - UNIVERSITY HEALTH NETWORK

November 2015

• 1000 CAD

Speech-Language Pathology Travel Award

Toronto, Canada

University of Toronto

March 2014

• 425 CAD

School of Graduate Studies Conference Grant

Toronto, Canada

University of Toronto

November 2014

• 850 CAD

Undergraduate College Scholarship

Cork, Ireland

University College Cork

May 2010

• 1000 EUR

Professional Affiliations and Service

Professional Associations

2018-Present

- Non-Clinical Member, American Speech-Language-Hearing Association (ASHA)
- Postdoctoral Member, Society for the Neurobiology of Language (SNL)

Manuscript Reviews

2018–Present

- American Journal of Speech-Language Pathology, Reviews: 7
- Journal of Speech, Language, and Hearing Research, Reviews: 6
- Neurorehabilitation and Neural Repair, Reviews: 2
- Journal of Communication Disorders, Reviews: 1
- Journal of Voice, Reviews: 1
- · Clinical Linguistics & Phonetics, Reviews: 1

Conference Reviews

2019-2020

- International Clinical Phonetics and Linguistics Association Symposium 2020/21
- Boston Speech Motor Control Symposium 2019

Grant Reviews

2019-2020

• LVST Small Student Grant

Boston, MA

Organizing Committee, Boston Speech Motor Control Symposium 2019

Publications

Available for download at https://www.elaine-kearney.com/publication/

Peer-Reviewed

Contributions of auditory and somatosensory feedback to vocal motor control

SMITH, D. J., STEPP, C. E., GUENTHER, F. H., & KEARNEY, E.

A simple 3-parameter model for examining adaptation in speech and voice production

KEARNEY, E., NIETO-CASTANON, A., WEERATHUNGE, H. R., FALSINI, R., DALIRI, A., ABUR, D., BALLARD, K. J., CHANG, S-E.,

Chao, S-C., Heller Murray, E. S., Scott, T. L., & Guenther, F. H.

Articulating: The neural mechanisms of speech production

KEARNEY, E., & GUENTHER, F. H.

Towards movement-based outcome measures for apraxia of speech: A systematic review

BAILEY, K., KEARNEY, E., ROBERTS, E., & YUNUSOVA, Y.

Electromagnetic articulography (EMA) for real-time feedback application: **Computational techniques**

HAWORTH, B., KEARNEY, E., FALOUTSOS, P., BALJKO, M., & YUNUSOVA, Y.

Augmented visual feedback-aided interventions in motor rehabilitation in Parkinson's disease: A systematic review

KEARNEY, E., SHELLIKERI, S., MARTINO, R., & YUNUSOVA, Y.

Treating speech-movement hypokinesia in Parkinson's disease: Does movement size

matter and to what extent?

KEARNEY, E., HAWORTH, M. B., SCHOLL, J., FALOUTSOS, P., BALJKO, M., & YUNUSOVA, Y.

Sentence-level movements in Parkinson's disease: Loud, clear, and slow speech

KEARNEY, E., GILES, R., HAWORTH, M. B., FALOUTSOS, P., BALJKO, M., & YUNUSOVA, Y.

disease

YUNUSOVA, Y., KEARNEY, E., KULKARNI, M., HAWORTH, M. B., BALJKO, M., & FALOUTSOS, P.

Outcome measures in developmental speech sound disorders with a motor basis

Kearney, E., Granata, F., Yunusova, Y., van Lieshout, P., Hayden, D., & Namasivayam, A.

Motor Speech Treatment Protocol for developmental motor speech disorders

Namasivayam, A., Pukonen, M., Hard, J., Jahnke, R., Kearney, E., Kroll, R., & van Lieshout, P.

Tongue-palate contact during selected vowels in children with speech sound disorders

LEE, A., GIBBON, F. E., KEARNEY, E., & MURPHY, D.

Electromagnetic articulography in the development of "serious games" for speech rehabilitation

HAWORTH, M. B., KEARNEY, E., BALJKO, M., FALOUTSOS, P., & YUNUSOVA, Y.

Journal of Speech, Language, and

Hearing Research

Frontiers in Psychology

Language, Cognition, and

Neuroscience

2019

Aphasiology

Computer Methods in Biomechanics and Biomedical Engineering:

Imaging and Visualization

2019

Disability and Rehabilitation

Journal of Speech, Language, and Hearing Research

Journal of Speech, Language, and

Hearing Research

Game-based augmented visual feedback for enlarging speech movements in Parkinson's Journal of Speech, Language, and

Hearing Research

Current Developmental Disorders

Developmental Neurorehabilitation

International Journal of Speech-Language Pathology

2014

Proceedings from PMHA 2014: The 2nd International Workshop on Biomechanical and Parametric Modeling of Human Anatomy

2014

Proceedings

Presentations Contributions of auditory and somatosensory feedback to vocal motor control Santa Barbara, CA KEARNEY, E., SMITH, D. J, STEPP, C. E, & GUENTHER, F. H. • 20th Biennial Conference on Motor Speech SimpleDIVA: A 3-parameter model for examining adaptation in speech and voice Helsinki, Finland production KEARNEY, E., NIETO-CASTANON, A., DALIRI, A., & GUENTHER, F. H. 2019 11th Annual Meeting of the Society for Neurobiology of Language Investigating the Neural Mechanisms of Speech Rate, Clarity, and Emphasis. Boston Boston, MA **Speech Motor Control Symposium** KEARNEY, E., TOURVILLE, J.A., NIETO-CASTANON, A., & GUENTHER, F. 2019 Boston Speech Motor Control Symposium A 3-parameter model for fitting and interpreting speech sensorimotor adaptation data San Francisco, CA GUENTHER, F., KEARNEY, E., DALIRI, A., & NIETO-CASTANON, A. 2019 • Neural Bases of Speech Production The speech movement disorder in Parkinson's disease and its rehabilitation using Boston, MA augmented visual feedback KEARNEY, E., HAWORTH, M. B., FALOUTSOS, P., BALJKO, M., & YUNUSOVA, Y. 2017 Boston Speech Motor Control Working Group Game-based speech therapy using visual feedback in Parkinson's disease Groningen, Netherlands KEARNEY, E., HAWORTH, B., SCHOLL, J., GILES, R., FALOUTSOS, P., BALJKO, M., & YUNUSOVA, Y. • 7th International Conference on Speech Motor Control The speech movement disorder and its rehabilitation in Parkinson's disease using Montreal, Canada augmented visual feedback KEARNEY, E., HAWORTH, M. B., FALOUTSOS, P., BALJKO, M., & YUNUSOVA, Y. 2017 • Universite de Montreal Speech movements in apraxia of speech Calgary, Canada ROBERTS, E., KEARNEY, E., BAILEY, K., GRAHAM, N., ROCHON, E., & YUNUSOVA, Y. 2017 · Canadian Stroke Congress Game-based augmented visual feedback treatment for apraxia of speech after stroke Calgary, Canada Yunusova, Y., Kearney, E., Scholl, J., Janik-Jones, C., Haworth, B., Roberts, E., Faloutsos, P., & Baljko, M. 2017 • Canadian Stroke Congress Speech movements and intelligibility in Parkinson's disease Newport Beach, CA KEARNEY, E., SHELLIKERI, S., GILES, R., HAWORTH, M. B., FALOUTSOS, P., BALJKO, M., & YUNUSOVA, Y. 2016 • 18th Biennial Conference on Motor Speech Movement-based speech therapy for dysarthria in Parkinson's disease and apraxia of Newport Beach, CA speech Yunusova, Y., Kearney, E., Haworth, M. B., Faloutsos, P., & Baljko, M. • 18th Biennial Conference on Motor Speech Development of augmented feedback targets for speech rehabilitation in Parkinson's Cork, Ireland disease

KEARNEY, E., HAWORTH, M. B., FALOUTSOS, P., BALJKO, M., & YUNUSOVA, Y.

· University College Cork

Measuring participation in developmental speech sound disorders with a motor basis

Kearney, E., Granata, F., Yunusova, Y., van Lieshout, P., Hayden, D., & Namasivayam, A.

· American Speech-Language-Hearing Association Convention

Instrumental outcome measures in developmental speech sound disorders with a motor basis

Granata, F., Kearney, E., Yunusova, Y., van Lieshout, P., Hayden, D., & Namasivayam, A.

• International Association of Orofacial Myology Convention

Artifact removal techniques for 3D electromagnetic articulography

Moghaddam, A., Haworth, B., Kearney, E., Faloutsos, P., Baljko, M., & Yunusova, Y.

3rd International Workshop on Biomechanical and Parametric Modeling of Human Anatomy

Denver, CO 2015

Orlando FI

2015

Montreal, Canada

2015

4

Articulatory working space in older adults across speaking conditions

Kearney, E., Haworth, M. B., Faloutsos, P., Baljko, M., & Yunusova, Y.

American Speech-Language-Hearing Association Convention

Electromagnetic articulography in the development of serious games for speech rehabilitation

Vancouver, Canada

Orlando, FL

2014

2014

HAWORTH, M. B., KEARNEY, E., BALJKO, M., FALOUTSOS, P., YUNUSOVA, Y.

• 2nd International Workshop on Biomechanical and Parametric Modeling of Human Anatomy

Articulatory working space as a kinematic target in augmented feedback applications

Kearney, E., Haworth, M. B., Faloutsos, P., Baljko, M., & Yunusova, Y.

Sarasota, FL 2014

• . 17th Biennial Conference on Motor Speech

Rehabilitative speech computer game calibration using empirical characterizations of articulatory working space

Sarasota, FL

Yunusova, Y., Faloutsos, P., & Baljko, M.

2014

• . 17th Biennial Conference on Motor Speech

Tongue-palate contact during selected vowels in children with speech sound disorder of unknown origin

Cork, Ireland

2012

2011

LEE, A., KEARNEY, E., & GIBBON, F. E.

• International Clinical Phonetics and Linguistics Association Conference

Tongue-palate contact during selected vowels in children with speech sound disorder of

unknown origin Lee, A., Kearney, E., & Gibbon, F. E. Dublin, Ireland

• Irish Association of Speech and Language Therapists Biennial Conference

Software_

SimpleDIVA https://bit.ly/2XY1n7f

Kearney, E., Nieto-Castanon, A., Falsini, R., Kearney, E. & Weerathunge, H.R.

2019

· An app that allows users to apply a simplified version of the DIVA model to data collected from auditory sensorimotor adaptation experiments

Teaching Experience ____

Research Methods in Speech-Language Pathology and Audiology

Boston University

Course Instructor

September 2019-December 2019

Research to Practice, Principles of Clinical Practice

University of Toronto

Course Instructor

September 2017-December 2017

Neuroanatomy for Motor Speech Disorders, Motor Speech Disorders

University of Toronto

GUEST LECTURER

September 2015

Principles of Motor Learning, Motor Speech Disorders

University of Toronto

GUEST LECTURER

September 2014

Technology for Assessment and Intervention in Motor Speech Disorders, Motor Speech Disorders

University of Toronto

GUEST LECTURER

September 2014

Quantitative Methods, Linguistics in the Workforce: Clinical Practice and Research.

University of Toronto

GUEST LECTURER

October 2016

Boston University

SimpleDIVA Software Tutorial, Neural Control of SpeechGUEST LECTURER

November 2019

Introduction to Motor Speech Disorders, Adult Language Disorders

University of Toronto

GUEST LECTURER

November 2015

Communicative Excellence, Advanced Principles of Clinical Practice

University of Toronto

GUEST LECTURER

March 2016

Advancements in Treatment for Dysarthria, Neuromotor Speech Disorders

GUEST LECTURER

"Outcome Measures in Articulation Disorders, Articulation and Related Disorders **GUEST LECTURER**

Outcome Measures in Developmental Speech Sound Disorders With a Motor Basis, Research in Speech-Language Pathology

GUEST LECTURER

Massachusetts General Hospital -Institute of Health Professions July 2019

> University of Toronto February 2016

> University of Toronto

April 2015

Technical Skills_____

Speech Acoustics

PRAAT, AUDACITY, TF32

Speech Kinematics

ELECTROMAGNETIC ARTICULOGRAPHY, SPEECH MOVEMENT ANALYSIS FOR SPEECH AND HEARING RESEARCH (SMASH)

Auditory Feedback Perturbation

AUDAPTER

Signal Processing and Analysis

MATLAB

Neuroimaging Analysis

STATISTICAL PARAMETRIC MAPPING (SPM), FREESURFER, FUNCTIONAL CONNECTIVITY TOOLBOX (CONN)

Statistical Analysis

R, MATLAB

Version Control

GітНив

Design Software

AFFINITY DESIGNER, ADOBE INDESIGN

Bibliographic Management

Endnote, Zotero